<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8' standalone='no'?>
<doxygen xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="compound.xsd" version="1.9.8" xml:lang="en-US">
  <compounddef id="md_build_2md__files_2docs_2design" kind="page">
    <compoundname>md_build_2md__files_2docs_2design</compoundname>
    <title>Design Considerations for Event-Driven Programming in C++</title>
    <briefdescription>
    </briefdescription>
    <detaileddescription>
<para><anchor id="md_build_2md__files_2docs_2design_1autotoc_md24"/></para>
<para>This document outlines the design principles and architectural decisions behind the event-driven programming examples in this project. It is intended to provide insight into the trade-offs, patterns, and best practices used when implementing various event-handling mechanisms in C++.</para>
<sect1 id="md_build_2md__files_2docs_2design_1autotoc_md25">
<title>Overview</title>
<para>Event-driven programming is built around the idea of responding to events as they occur, rather than following a strict linear execution flow. This project showcases multiple techniques—including the Observer pattern, callbacks, Qt signal-slot mechanisms, I/O event handling with <computeroutput>select()</computeroutput>/<computeroutput>poll()</computeroutput>, and message queues—each with its own design considerations.</para>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="md_build_2md__files_2docs_2design_1autotoc_md26">
<title>Key Design Patterns and Concepts</title>
<sect2 id="md_build_2md__files_2docs_2design_1autotoc_md27">
<title>1. Observer Pattern</title>
<para><itemizedlist>
<listitem><para><bold>Decoupling:</bold> <linebreak/>
 The Observer pattern helps decouple the event source (subject) from the event handlers (observers). This makes it easier to extend and maintain the system.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><bold>Scalability:</bold> <linebreak/>
 By allowing multiple observers to register, the pattern scales well as more components are added.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><bold>Flexibility:</bold> <linebreak/>
 Observers can be added or removed at runtime without changing the underlying subject logic.</para>
</listitem></itemizedlist>
</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="md_build_2md__files_2docs_2design_1autotoc_md28">
<title>2. Callbacks and Function Pointers</title>
<para><itemizedlist>
<listitem><para><bold>Simplicity:</bold> <linebreak/>
 Callbacks (using function pointers or <computeroutput>std::function</computeroutput>) provide a straightforward way to handle events.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><bold>Modularity:</bold> <linebreak/>
 Using lambdas or callable objects promotes modularity, enabling concise and flexible event handling.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><bold>Trade-offs:</bold> <linebreak/>
 Debugging and maintaining callback-based code can sometimes be challenging, particularly when the flow of control is not linear.</para>
</listitem></itemizedlist>
</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="md_build_2md__files_2docs_2design_1autotoc_md29">
<title>3. Qt Signal-Slot Mechanism</title>
<para><itemizedlist>
<listitem><para><bold>Framework Integration:</bold> <linebreak/>
 The Qt framework abstracts much of the complexity of event handling with its built-in signal-slot system, which is especially useful in GUI applications.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><bold>Type Safety and Readability:</bold> <linebreak/>
 Qt&apos;s meta-object system ensures type safety and clarity in the connections between signals and slots.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><bold>Tooling Requirements:</bold> <linebreak/>
 Utilizing Qt requires the use of the Meta-Object Compiler (moc) and is best suited for applications already leveraging the Qt framework.</para>
</listitem></itemizedlist>
</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="md_build_2md__files_2docs_2design_1autotoc_md30">
<title>4. I/O Event Handling with &lt;tt&gt;select()&lt;/tt&gt;/&lt;tt&gt;poll()&lt;/tt&gt;</title>
<para><itemizedlist>
<listitem><para><bold>Low-Level Control:</bold> <linebreak/>
 These system calls provide fine-grained control over I/O operations, making them suitable for network programming or scenarios where performance is critical.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><bold>Scalability Considerations:</bold> <linebreak/>
 While <computeroutput>select()</computeroutput> can be sufficient for a small number of file descriptors, <computeroutput>poll()</computeroutput> or more advanced mechanisms like <computeroutput>epoll</computeroutput> (Linux) or <computeroutput>kqueue</computeroutput> (BSD) may be more appropriate as the number of connections grows.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><bold>Complexity:</bold> <linebreak/>
 The use of these system calls requires careful handling of file descriptors and error conditions, adding complexity to the code.</para>
</listitem></itemizedlist>
</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="md_build_2md__files_2docs_2design_1autotoc_md31">
<title>5. Message/Event Queues</title>
<para><itemizedlist>
<listitem><para><bold>Sequential Processing:</bold> <linebreak/>
 An event queue allows events to be stored and processed sequentially, which can simplify the management of asynchronous tasks.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><bold>Concurrency:</bold> <linebreak/>
 When used in multi-threaded environments, queues help in coordinating the processing of events, although synchronization mechanisms (e.g., mutexes) might be necessary.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><bold>Flexibility:</bold> <linebreak/>
 Message queues can be used to decouple the generation and handling of events, making the system more robust and easier to extend.</para>
</listitem></itemizedlist>
</para>
</sect2>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="md_build_2md__files_2docs_2design_1autotoc_md32">
<title>Architectural Considerations</title>
<sect2 id="md_build_2md__files_2docs_2design_1autotoc_md33">
<title>Decoupling and Modularity</title>
<para><itemizedlist>
<listitem><para><bold>Loose Coupling:</bold> <linebreak/>
 A key benefit of event-driven design is the decoupling of event producers from consumers. This results in a more modular and flexible architecture where components can be developed, tested, and maintained independently.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><bold>Extensibility:</bold> <linebreak/>
 New event types and handlers can be added with minimal impact on existing code, allowing the system to evolve over time.</para>
</listitem></itemizedlist>
</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="md_build_2md__files_2docs_2design_1autotoc_md34">
<title>Concurrency and Responsiveness</title>
<para><itemizedlist>
<listitem><para><bold>Asynchronous Processing:</bold> <linebreak/>
 Many event-driven applications need to remain responsive while handling multiple events concurrently. This may require the use of threading, asynchronous I/O, or specialized event loops.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><bold>Performance Trade-offs:</bold> <linebreak/>
 The asynchronous nature of event-driven programming can introduce overhead in context switching and synchronization. Careful design is needed to ensure that the responsiveness benefits outweigh these costs.</para>
</listitem></itemizedlist>
</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="md_build_2md__files_2docs_2design_1autotoc_md35">
<title>Error Handling and Debugging</title>
<para><itemizedlist>
<listitem><para><bold>Non-linear Execution:</bold> <linebreak/>
 With event-driven programming, the flow of execution can be non-linear, making debugging more challenging. Incorporating robust error handling and logging mechanisms is essential.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><bold>State Management:</bold> <linebreak/>
 Keeping track of the application&apos;s state across various asynchronous events is crucial to avoid race conditions and ensure consistency.</para>
</listitem></itemizedlist>
</para>
</sect2>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="md_build_2md__files_2docs_2design_1autotoc_md36">
<title>Best Practices</title>
<para><itemizedlist>
<listitem><para><bold>Clear Separation of Concerns:</bold> <linebreak/>
 Ensure that event producers, consumers, and the mechanisms linking them are clearly separated to promote maintainability.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><bold>Use of Modern C++ Features:</bold> <linebreak/>
 Leverage C++20 features, such as lambdas and concepts, to write more expressive and type-safe code.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><bold>Robust Testing:</bold> <linebreak/>
 Due to the asynchronous nature of event-driven systems, thorough testing (including unit tests and integration tests) is essential to identify potential issues early.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><bold>Documentation and Logging:</bold> <linebreak/>
 Maintain detailed documentation and implement logging to trace event flow and aid in debugging.</para>
</listitem></itemizedlist>
</para>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="md_build_2md__files_2docs_2design_1autotoc_md37">
<title>Conclusion</title>
<para>The design of an event-driven system requires balancing flexibility, performance, and maintainability. This project demonstrates multiple approaches to handling events in C++, each with its own strengths and trade-offs. By understanding these design principles and patterns, you can choose the most appropriate approach for your application and build robust, responsive systems.</para>
<para>Feel free to explore the individual documentation files for each event-handling mechanism to gain a deeper understanding of their specific implementations and use cases. </para>
</sect1>
    </detaileddescription>
    <location file="build/md_files/docs/design.md"/>
  </compounddef>
</doxygen>
